Guide to the Leonard C. Hosford Scrapbooks 1811-1957
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Leonard C. Hosford Scrapbooks
1811-1957
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Mss2195
Hosford, Leonard C., 1885 -- 1961
5 cubic feet (35 volumes in 4 document cases and 16 custom boxes)
Compilation of historical research and photographs on steamboating in the western and central United States and Canada from 1811 to 1957. Collection comprised of thirty five volumes assembled by steamboat captain Leonard C. Hosford.
Biography of Leonard C. Hosford:
Born into steamboating, Leonard C. Hosford began work on the river with his father at age 18. The senior Hosford, Olin W., founded the Hosford Transportation Company in 1906 with sons Leonard and O. J. and prospered in the business of towing logs for the many sawmills along the Willamette River. Leonard continued this affiliation until his death in 1961.
Leonard C. Hosford married Illinois native Marion Kelly and resided in Portland for his entire life. His wife and a daughter, Nancy McClellan, survived him, along with six grandchildren. A retired steamboat captain, Hosford was a member of the Veteran Steamboat Men's Association. His love for the history of steamboating is clearly in evidence in the extensive record compiled in this collection.
This collection includes typewritten text, photographs, and other illustrations relating to the history of steamboating in the western and central United States and Canada. A few articles of related interest by other authors comprise one of the thirty five volumes, compiled by Leonard C. Hosford. Several volumes include index of illustrations.
The collection is arranged in the following series:
Series A: History of stern and side wheel steamboats on the Columbia, Snake, and Willamette Rivers in Oregon, Washington, Idaho, Montana in United States of America and British Columbia, Canada, 1835-1947
Series B: History of steamboats in Washington, California, Utah, Alaska, and Canada, 1835-1937
Series C: History of stern and side wheel steamboats on the Ohio, Mississippi, Missouri and their tributaries, also the Red River of the North in United States and Canada, 1811-1940
Series D: Hosford Steamboats, 1887-1934
Series E: Pictures and records of steamboats, 1847-1957
Subseries 1: Columbia River, 1858-1907
Subseries 2: Rivers in California and Colorado, 1847-1957
Subseries 3: Pictures and records of steamboats on the Columbia, Snake, Willamette, and Yamhill Rivers in Oregon, Washington and Idaho, 1853-1938
Subseries 4: Puget Sound and Skagit River, Washington, 1857-1914
Subseries 5: Canada and Alaska, 1865-1937
Series F: Index of Steamboat Records, undated
The collection is open to the public.
Gift of Mrs. Leonard C. Hosford, September 1967
"Leonard C. Hosford," Oregonian (Portland), 16 September 1961, p. 9, c. 3.
"Leonard Hosford," Oregon Journal (Portland), 18 September 1961, p. 5, c. 1.
"O. W. Hosford," in Charles Henry Carey, History of Oregon, volume 2: Biographical (Chicago: Pioneer Historical Publishing Company, 1922), 294-7.
David L. Stearns Papers, MSS 2099, Oregon Historical Society Research Library
Transportation Collection, MSS 1506, Oregon Historical Society Research Library
The collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings:
Hosford, Leonard C.; Hosford, Olin W.; Jenkin, Kenneth
Hosford Transportation Company
Steamboats--Canada--History.; Steamboats--West (U.S.)--History.; Steamboats -- Willamette River (Or.)--History.
Alaska; Idaho; Oregon; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Transportation; Washington (State)
Photographs; Scrapbooks
- History of stern and side wheel steamboats on the Columbia, Snake, and Willamette Rivers in Oregon, Washington, Idaho, Montana in United States of America and British Columbia, Canada from 1835 through 1947, Series A; 5 volumes.
  - Volume 1. Steamboat Records, 1835-1879 (Volume 1)
    Chapters 1-3. Photographs captioned; index of illustrations.
  - Volume 2. Steamboat Records, 1880-1947 (Volume 2)
    Chapters 4-7. Photographs captioned but not indexed.
  - 1835-1947 (Volume 3)
    Captioned illustrations only, no text. 35 photographs; 35 images absent.
  - 1835-1947 (Volume 4)
    Entire text in one volume. Photographs neither captioned nor indexed.
  - 1835-1947 (Volume 5)
    Text is exact carbon of volume 4.
- History of steamboats in Washington, California, Utah, Alaska, and Canada, 1835-1937; Series B; 5 volumes
  - History of stern, sidewheel, propeller steamboats on Puget Sound, Gray's Harbor, Skagit, Snohomish, Samish, Puyallup Rivers [in] Washington, USA from 1835 to 1941 and sternwheel steamboats in British Columbia, Canada, on Fraser, Skeena, Stickeen Rivers from 1835 to 1913, by Lenard C. Hosford. Chapters 1-10, with index of illustrations. (Volume 6)
  - History of stern and side wheel steamboats on the Sacramento, San Joaquin, and Napa Rivers and San Francisco, San Pablo, Susuin, Humbolt Bays -- Peteluma Creek, California, and the Great Salt Lake, Utah -- Colorado River from 1847 through 1926. 7 chapters; index of illustrations for Chapters 1-6. This volume is designated on its cover as Volume Four by Kenneth Jenkin and Lenard C. Hosford. (Volume 7)
  - History of sternwheel steamboats -- Kuskuwin, Yukon, Koyukuk, and Tanana in Alaska, USA and Yukon, Stewart, Lewes Rivers and the Lakes Bennett and Teslin in Yukon Territory, Canada, from 1869 to 1937 on Peace, Athabasca, Slave, and MacKenie Rivers [in] Alberta and Northwest Territory on Assiniboin, Saskatchewan Rivers in Manitoba, Canada, and Red River of the North in Canada and United States from 1861 to 1898, by Leonard C. Hosford. 7 chapters, captioned illustrations, index of illustrations. (Volume 8)
  - Steamboat pictures, 1849-1933 (Volume 9)
    Collected by Leonard C. Hosford. 57 photographs, 2 tintypes, 57 photographs absent. Photographs captioned; no text or index.
  - Articles on steamboat history, undated (Volume 10)
    "Famous pioneer steamboats of Puget Sound" by William O. Thorniley, "History of Northwest Steamboating," by H. C. Lord, and newspaper clippings relating to Sauvie Island and the Eliza Anderson. Articles repaginated and reformatted in 3-ring binder by Hosford.
- History of stern and side wheel steamboats on the Ohio, Mississippi, Missouri and their tributaries, also the Red River of the North in United States and Canada, 1811-1940; Series C; 5 volumes
  - Volume 1, 1811 to 1870 (Volume 11)
    Chapters 1-4. Text plus captioned illustrations; index of 109 illustrations.
  - Volume 2, 1871 to 1883 (Volume 12)
    Chapters 5-6 and supplement. Text plus captioned illustrations; index of 149 illustrations.
  - Volume 3, 1885 to 1895 (Volume 13)
    Chapters 7-8. Contains index of 125 illustrations, 1 loose photo, text.
  - Volume 4, 1896 to 1905 (Volume 14)
    Chapters 9-10. Text plus captioned illustrations; index of 118 illustrations.
  - Volume 5, 1906-1940 (Volume 15)
    Chapters 11-14. Text plus 116 captioned illustrations; no index.
- Hosford Steamboats., 1887-1934; Series D; 1 volume
  - Volume 16, 1887-1934 (Box-folder 1/1)
    Captain Olin W. Hosford -- Steamboats he owned or had interest in Columbia and Willamette Rivers from 1887 to 1934.
    Contains views of harbors, Portland, Oregon vicinity. 29 illustrations with brief descriptions.
- Pictures and records of steamboats., 1847-1957; Series E; 15 volumes
  - Columbia River., 1858-1907; Sub-series 1; 1 volume in 1 folder
    - Volume 17, 1858-1907 (Box-folder 1/2)
      Steamers brought over Cascade Rapids of Columbia River, 1858-1907
      Columbia Transportation Co. steamer Telephone, 1884
      Captain E. W. Spencer steamer Chas. R. Spencer, 1901
      White Collar Line steamers Telephone and Bailey Gatzert, 1884-1890
      40 illustrations with brief descriptions.
  - Rivers in California and Colorado., 1847-1957; Sub-series 2; 2 volumes in 2 folders
    - Volume 18, 1847-1957 (Box-folder 1/3)
      Sacramento and San Joaquin Rivers, San Francisco Bay steamboats.
      Colorado River history and steamboats.
      72 illustrations with brief descriptions; 2 pages text.
    - Volume 34, San Francisco Bay, Sacramento, and San Joaquin Rivers in California, USA, 1853-1926 (Box-folder 4/5)
      48 illustrations with descriptions.
  - Pictures and records of steamboats on the Columbia, Snake, Willamette, and Yamhill Rivers in Oregon, Washington and Idaho., 1853-1938; Sub-series 3; 9 volumes in 9 folders
    - Volume 19, Index of Steamboat Records, 1863-1900 (Box-folder 2/1)
      21 illustrations with descriptions.
    - Volume 20, 1872-1926 (Box-folder 2/2)
      29 illustrations with descriptions.
    - Volume 21, 1866-1918 (Box-folder 2/3)
      32 illustrations with descriptions.
    - Volume 22, 1857-1909 (Box-folder 2/4)
      20 illustrations with descriptions.
    - Volume 23, 1853-1933 (Box-folder 2/5)
      46 illustrations with descriptions.
    - Volume 24, 1877-1912 (Box-folder 2/6)
      22 illustrations with descriptions.
    - Volume 25, 1884-1914 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Volume 26, 1862-1912 (Box-folder 3/2)
      26 illustrations with descriptions.
    - Volume 27, 1884-1938 (Box-folder 3/3)
      27 illustrations with descriptions.
  - Puget Sound and Skagit River, Washington, 1857-1914; Sub-series 4; 2 volumes in 2 folders
    - Volume 28, Puget Sound and Skagit River, Washington, 1876-1912 (Box-folder 3/4)
      31 illustrations with descriptions.
    - Volume 29, Puget Sound, Washington, 1857-1914 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Canada and Alaska., 1865-1937; Sub-series 5; 4 volumes in 4 folders
    - Volume 30, Columbia and Kootenay Rivers in British Columbia, Canada, 1885-1914 (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Volume 31, Stickeen, Skeena, and Fraser Rivers in British Columbia, MacKenzie, Slave, Athabaska, Peace Rivers [in] Northwest Territory and Alberta, Canada, 1865-1922 (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Volume 32, Yukon, Koyukuk, Tanana, Kuskuwin in Alaska, USA and Yukon and Lewis Rivers in Yukon Territory, Canada, 1896-1899 (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Volume 33, Yukon, Koyukuk, Tanana, Kuskuwin in Alaska, USA and Yukon and Lewis Rivers in Yukon Territory, Canada, 1898-1937 (Box-folder 4/4)
- Index of Steamboat Records., Undated; Series F; 1 volume
  - Index of Steamboat Records for Books 1-25, undated (Volume 35)